Guide to the Cynthia Macdonald Papers
University of Houston Libraries
- Correspondence
  - Writing Submission and Solicitation Correspondence
    - Red, White, & Blues (Box 18, Folder 61)
    - River Styx (Box 18, Folder 62)
    - Shenandoah (Box 18, Folder 63)
    - Sonora Review (Box 18, Folder 64)
    - The Southern Review (Box 18, Folder 65)
    - Southwest Review (Box 18, Folder 66)
    - Spirituality & Health (Box 18, Folder 67)
    - Stockpot (Box 18, Folder 68)
    - Stone Country (Box 18, Folder 69)
    - Sumac (Box 18, Folder 70)
    - Texas Anthology (Box 18, Folder 71)
    - Texas in Poetry (Box 18, Folder 72)
    - The Texas Review (Box 18, Folder 73)
    - 13th Moon (Box 18, Folder 74)
    - TriQuarterly (Box 18, Folder 75)
    - Woman Poet (Box 18, Folder 76)
    - Women’s Poetry Anthology (Box 18, Folder 77)
    - The Yale Review (Box 18, Folder 78)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    The correspondence in this sub-series is neither to nor from Cynthia Macdonald, and is arranged alphabetically by the senders’ last names. Among the items are 12 letters to Donald Barthelme; 19 invitees’ responses to singer Judy Collins for a party she was throwing for Cynthia Macdonald; letters from John Barth, Adrienne Rich, and Studs Terkel; and one letter in the “First Names Only” folder from a book editor at Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. to American music composer Jerome Kern.
    - A – M (Box 18, Folder 79)
    - N – Z (Box 18, Folder 80)
    - First names only (Box 18, Folder 81)
- Writing Career
  This series documents Cynthia Macdonald’s career and life as a writer. Contents include material related to poetry readings; writers’ conferences; reviews of her poetry; publishing contracts; publicity photographs; fellowship and NEA grant applications; prizes and awards; news clippings; royalty statements; her professional biography and curriculum vitae; other writers’ curricula vitae; letters of recommendation; the judging of writing contests; and documents regarding professional affiliations (such as PEN and the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters). The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not.
  - Posters, festival programs, proofs of book cover art (Ovs box 1, Folder 1)
  - Eight posters from readings, publicity, and festivals (Ovs box 2, Folder 1)
  - Five posters from readings and other events (Drawer F.9, Ovs folder 15)
- Writings by Others
  This series contains Cynthia Macdonald’s collection of works by other writers, including students, writer friends, famous authors, entrants in writing contests, and others. Material includes manuscripts, typescripts, printed material, and photocopies of works published in books and magazines. The series also includes some writing about other writers, organized by Cynthia Macdonald according to the subjects’ names. Of particular interest are original works by noteworthy authors, arranged alphabetically by the authors’ last names in Box 22. These materials include handwritten and typewritten copies of original drafts, as opposed to photocopies of published pieces. The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not.
  - Max Apple – essay (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Daniel Bourne – manuscript for book of poems (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Lucie Brock-Broido – poems (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Lucie Brock-Broido – poems (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Sharon Bryan – poems (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Sharon Bryan – manuscript of memoir (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Scott Cairns – manuscript for book of poems (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Vikram Chandra – fiction (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Jane Cooper – poems (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Jane Cooper – poems (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Blaga Dimitrova – poems translated into English from Bulgarian (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Leon Driskell – poems (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Nick Flynn – poems (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Marilyn Hacker – poems and essay (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Edward Hirsch – essay (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Galway Kinnell – poem (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - John Lienhard – speech (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Philip Lopate – essay (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - Molly Peacock – poems (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - Patty Seyburn – poems (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - Tom Sleigh – poem (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - Susan Sontag – play, “Alice in Bed” (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - Pimone Triplett – manuscript for book of poems (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - Pimone Triplett – manuscript for book of poems (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Sidney Wade – poems (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - Lois Parkinson Zamora – essay (Box 22, Folder 26)
  - Lisa Zeidner – prose poem for M.A. thesis and poems (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Lisa Zeidner – manuscript for book of short stories (Box 22, Folder 28)
- Teaching Career
  The series spans Cynthia Macdonald’s career as a writing teacher at Sarah Lawrence College, Johns Hopkins University, and the University of Houston. Items include departmental memos and other school-related business; class materials such as handouts on poetry; her biography/curriculum vitae (filed by Macdonald with her teaching materials, instead of with the Writing Career series); some student writings (filed here by Macdonald, instead of with the Writings by Others series); faculty evaluations by students; notes to and from other faculty members; and faculty awards. The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not.
  - UH Creative Writing Program honor (Ovs box 1, Folder 2)
- Psychoanalysis Career
  This series contains documents from Cynthia Macdonald’s career as a professional psychoanalyst. Material includes papers and notes from her years as a psychoanalysis student; a certificate of graduation, agendas, and faculty memos from the Houston-Galveston Psychoanalytic Institute; printed materials on various psychoanalysis topics; research for her “Writing Blocks” work; items from the Aspen Institute Executive Seminar; and a (probably gag gift) Singing Sigmund Freud Pin filed in Box 32, Folder 1. The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not.
- Personal
  This series contains personal items collected over almost the entire course of Cynthia Macdonald’s life, from early childhood onward. Material includes artwork and schoolwork from her childhood; drawings and schoolwork by her sister, Virginia Lee, who passed away in childhood; summer camp documents and mementos; yearbooks; news clippings; photographs; mementos and documents from Macdonald’s children’s lives from childhood through adulthood; address books and day planners; travel documents such as maps, hotel and airline information, and mementos; shopping lists and Christmas gift lists; recipes; and posters. Contents of some boxes are described with the specific box numbers below; where not noted in detail, boxes contain an assortment of the above-mentioned materials. The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not. Box 33 contains one folder with Cynthia's father Leonard C. Lee's estate information; two folders with mementos of Cynthia's sister Virginia, who passed away in childhood; Cynthia's first baby shoe; several folders of travel documents; slides; photographs; and other items. Box 34 contains photographs, including many from Cynthia’s childhood, as well as unsorted negatives and slides.
  - posters, photos, awards, certificates, a large cloth with a sketch of Cynthia [by Hans Namuth?], and a plastic beaded “Muses” necklace (Ovs box 1, Item 1-13)
  - One classroom “Word Drill” poster from 1934; two oversize photos (Ovs box 2, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of baseball-related newspaper clippings, 1944 (Ovs box 3, Item 1)
  - One Helen Frankenthaler art poster; two homemade illustrated posters [by Jennifer Macdonald] (Drawer F.9, Ovs folder 16)
- Audiovisual
  This series contains one box of assorted media such as audio cassettes, VHS tapes, and compact discs. The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not.
- Electronic Media
  This series contains one box of computer discs and hard drives. The series was arranged in accordance with minimal processing standards to expedite its availability to researchers. Some folders have retained Cynthia Macdonald’s original labels and organization, while others have not.
- Family History
  Contained in three record boxes and one oversize box, the series comprises materials that pre-date Cynthia Macdonald’s birth in 1928 and materials dated during her lifetime that do not directly involve her (e.g. correspondence between her mother and her mother’s second husband). This section will be updated when processing is complete. Materials can be made available to researchers upon request; please email jgrob@uh.edu for assistance.